Hey, everyone. Welcome. Are you ready to unlock an English superpower?
皆さん、こんにちは。準備はいいですか？ 英語のスーパーパワーを解放しましょう。
I'm talking about the power to go from meh to wow.
「まあまあ」から「わお！」に変わる力です。
We're going to learn how to show big feelings, like surprise and excitement,
驚きや興奮といった大きな感情を表現する方法を学びます。
to make your English sound way more fun and, you know, alive.
英語をもっと楽しく、生き生きとしたものにしましょう。
Okay, so check this out. On the left, we've got this is a big house.
さて、こちらを見てください。左側には「大きな家があります」。
It's okay, I guess. It's correct. But it's kind of boring, right?
まあ、正しいけど、ちょっと退屈ですよね？
Now, listen to the right side. What a big house. Whoa!
右側を聞いてみてください。「なんて大きな家だ！わお！」
Can you feel the difference? That second one has energy.
違いを感じますか？二つ目にはエネルギーがあります。
It's what you'd actually shout if you saw a giant amazing castle in a movie.
映画で巨大な素晴らしい城を見たときに叫ぶような感じです。
That wow feeling, that's our goal today.
その「わお！」の感覚が今日の目標です。
So, how do we get that wow factor?
では、どうやってその「わお！」を得るのでしょうか？
Well, let's start with our first magic word, our first power-ups.
まずは最初の魔法の言葉、パワーアップから始めましょう。
And that word is, what?
その言葉は「なんて？」です。
Okay, let's begin with a super-normal, kinda textbook-y sentence.
では、普通の教科書的な文から始めましょう。
Our starting point is, this is a beautiful flower.
出発点は「美しい花です」。
Pretty simple, right?
シンプルですよね？
But don't worry, we're about to give it a serious upgrade.
でも心配しないで、これを大きくアップグレードします。
So the next step is super easy.
次のステップはとても簡単です。
All you gotta do is find the describing part, the adjective and the noun.
説明部分、形容詞と名詞を見つけるだけです。
In this case, it's a beautiful flower. Got it?
この場合は「美しい花」です。わかりましたか？
Now just take our magic word, what, and stick it right on the front.
次に、魔法の言葉「なんて？」を前に置くだけです。
And boom! Just like that, you've completely transformed the sentence.
はい！これで文が完全に変わりました。
Check it out. What a beautiful flower this is! Did you notice that?
見てください。「なんて美しい花なんだ！」気づきましたか？
that this is jumped all the way to the end, that's part of the magic.
「です」が最後に移動したのが魔法の一部です。
You've just made a real exclamatory sense.
これで本当に感嘆文ができました。
But hang on, here's a little secret.
でも、ちょっとした秘密があります。
When people are just talking, you know, in real life,
人々が普通に話しているとき、
they almost always make it shorter.
ほとんどいつも短くします。
They just chop off that ending part.
最後の部分を省略するのです。
So you'll usually just hear, what a beautiful flower.
だから、通常は「なんて美しい花だ」と聞こえます。
It just sounds more natural, more full of energy.
もっと自然でエネルギーに満ちています。
So let's break it down into a super simple formula,
では、これを超シンプルな公式に分解しましょう。
like a cheat code for English.
英語のチートコードのように。
It's just what, plus a or n, then an adjective, and then a noun.
「なんて？」、次に「a」または「n」、その後に形容詞、名詞です。
That's it. What a simple formula. See what I did there?
これだけです。シンプルな公式ですね。わかりましたか？
All right, you've mastered level one. Ready for the next power-up?
さあ、レベル1をマスターしました。 次のパワーアップの準備はいいですか？
Let's move on to our second magic word. This one is just as cool, and it's the word
次の魔法の言葉に進みましょう。 これも同じくらいクールな言葉です。
how. Now, for this one, we're going to start with a slightly different kind of sentence.
それは「どう？」です。今回は少し違う文から始めます。
Look closely. This flower is beautiful. See how the adjective beautiful comes after the verb
よく見てください。「この花は美しい」です。 形容詞「美しい」が動詞「です」の後に来ています。
is, that's a huge clue that we're going to use how.
これは「どう？」を使う大きなヒントです。
And the steps are just as easy as before.
手順は前と同じくらい簡単です。
First, find your describing word. Here, it's the adjective beautiful.
まず、説明する言葉を見つけます。ここでは形容詞「美しい」です。
Then, grab our second magic word, how, and put it right at the start.
次に、二つ目の魔法の言葉「どう？」を最初に置きます。
And there you go. Our new sentence is, how beautiful this flower is.
新しい文は「この花はどう美しい」です。
And yep, you guessed it, the subject and verb,
そして、そうです、主語と動詞、
this flower is, hop to the end again.
「この花は」がまた最後に移動します。
You're totally getting the hang of this.
これで完全にコツをつかみましたね。
And just like our what sentences,
「なんて？」の文と同様に、
You can make this one shorter and sound more natural too.
これも短くしてもっと自然に聞こえます。
Just drop the ending and you get a powerful, simple phrase.
最後を省略すると、力強くシンプルなフレーズになります。
How beautiful! You can use this for anything.
「どう美しい！」何にでも使えます。
See a cool new character in an anime? How cool!
アニメでクールなキャラクターを見たら？「どうクール！」
See a funny cat video online? How cute!
面白い猫の動画を見たら？「どう可愛い！」
So the formula for how is even simpler.
「どう？」の公式はさらにシンプルです。
It's just how, plus an adjective like beautiful
「どう？」、次に形容詞「美しい」や
or an adverb like fast. Imagine you're watching sports
副詞「速い」を加えます。スポーツを見ているときに
and your favorite player makes a run. You can yell, how fast he runs?
お気に入りの選手が走ったら、「どう速い！」と叫べます。
This one is super useful.
これはとても便利です。
Okay, so now you've got two awesome superpowers
さて、これで「なんて？」と「どう？」の 二つの素晴らしいスーパーパワーを手に入れました。
but that leads to the biggest, most important question.
でも、それは最も重要な質問につながります。
How do you know which one to use?
どれを使うか、どうやって知るの？
Well, don't worry, there is one secret rule that makes it so, so easy.
心配しないでください。とても簡単にする秘密のルールがあります。
All right, this is it, the big moment, the final piece of the puzzle
さあ、これがその瞬間、パズルの最後のピースです。
that's gonna make you an expert. Are you ready for the secret?
あなたを専門家にするためのものです。準備はいいですか？
Seriously, it's so simple. You're gonna be like,
本当に簡単です。あなたはこう思うでしょう。
Didn't anyone just tell me this before?
誰かがこれを教えてくれなかったの？
And the secret is a noun, that's it. That's the whole secret.
その秘密は名詞です。それが全てです。
All you have to do is look at the phrase
あなたがするべきことは、フレーズを見て
and ask yourself one question. Is there a noun in here?
自分に一つの質問をすることです。名詞はありますか？
If you see a noun, that's your answer. Let's look at this table.
名詞が見えたら、それが答えです。この表を見てみましょう。
It makes it super clear. For a nice car, do you see a noun?
とても明確です。「素敵な車」には名詞がありますか？
Yup, car, so we use what? Now look at how cute.
はい、車です。だから、何を使いますか？さて、「かわいい」の後に名詞はありますか？
Is there a noun right after cute? Nope, so we use how.
いいえ、だから「どうやって」を使います。
It really is that simple. The noun is the key to everything.
本当にそれだけ簡単です。名詞が全ての鍵です。
Okay, you've learned the formulas. You know the secret rule.
さて、あなたは公式を学びました。秘密のルールも知っています。
I think it's time to put your new superpower to the test.
新しいスーパーパワーを試す時が来ました。
Let's do a quick quiz. Ready? Let's go. Okay, first question.
クイッククイズをやりましょう。準備はいいですか？さあ、最初の質問です。
Imagine your friend shows you a new outfit
友達が新しい服を見せてくれます。
they're really excited about. You wanna say, ah, a pretty dress.
彼らはとても興奮しています。「ああ、素敵なドレス」と言いたいです。
So what goes in the blank? Look for the secret key. Do you see a noun?
空欄には何が入りますか？秘密の鍵を探してください。名詞は見えますか？
And the answer is, what? Of course, why?
答えは「何」です。もちろん、なぜなら？
Because we have the noun dress right there. A noun means you use what?
ドレスという名詞がそこにあるからです。名詞があると「何」を使います。
You totally got it. What a smart student you are.
あなたは完全に理解しました。賢い生徒ですね。
All right, round two. You're watching an action movie
さて、ラウンド2です。アクション映画を見ています。
and your favorite actor is running like crazy.
お気に入りの俳優が狂ったように走っています。
You wanna say, blank, fast he runs. Okay, think about it.
「空欄、速く走る」と言いたいです。考えてみてください。
What's the word after the blank? Is fast a noun?
空欄の後の言葉は何ですか？「速い」は名詞ですか？
The answer is how, awesome job. Fast isn't a noun here.
答えは「どうやって」です。素晴らしい仕事です。速いは名詞ではありません。
It's describing how he runs. So no noun means you use how. See?
彼がどうやって走るかを説明しています。名詞がないので「どうやって」を使います。分かりましたか？
Once you know the secret, it's actually really easy.
秘密を知ると、実際にはとても簡単です。
Before we finish, I wanna give you
終わる前に、
one more super useful everyday phrase, what a day.
もう一つ、日常で役立つフレーズを教えます。「なんて日だ」。
Now what's really cool is this is kind of like
これが面白いのは、これは日本の
a famous phrase in Japan, none de hida.
有名なフレーズ「なんで日だ」に似ています。
And you can use it for good days and bad days.
良い日にも悪い日にも使えます。
Like if you got a perfect score on your test,
テストで満点を取ったら、
you can say, wow, what a day.
「わあ、なんて日だ」と言えます。
But if you missed your bus and it started raining,
でも、バスを逃して雨が降り始めたら、
you can say, uh, what a day. It all depends on how you say it.
「うーん、なんて日だ」と言えます。言い方次第です。
So there you have it. Your new superpower is officially unlocked.
これであなたの新しいスーパーパワーが正式に解放されました。
The next time you see something cool or funny or totally surprising,
次に面白いことや驚くべきことを見たら、
don't just keep it in your head, say it out loud.
頭の中に留めずに声に出して言ってください。
What an awesome video game. How delicious this ramen is.
「なんて素晴らしいビデオゲームだろう」「このラーメンはなんて美味しいんだ」。
Go out there and start describing the amazing things you see.
外に出て、見た素晴らしいものを描写し始めてください。
Your English is gonna sound so much more exciting. Now go try it.
あなたの英語はもっとエキサイティングに聞こえるでしょう。さあ、試してみてください。